[Music]
Remember how many classes we have for
Bandit? A four-
part rate check I'm going to probably need one more
class just to finish the two-part test I want
today so I need one more extra
class for finishing all of the two proofs I have four
classes last year already I'm having an extra class for finishing all of the four classes last year already I'm having
faculty go talk we have four
good fine then I'm not I'm not too bad about
writing the cumsom to not a ba a l over write some
defining that as a c a a okay then if I
rat c a ma a it ln of a ma a did a andan a can d c a a pw
son so fath just like a
function just substitute make my
life a little better right
so the goal now as I mention lr is
to upper bound this expectation right so I will never
play a suboptimal one more than this many
times okay it's Ashley what we are
trying to show
okay so one one another  Notation I'll just
adopt the notation used in the proof
here even though we'll introduce different
notation in the previous class for the same thing it makes sense
for
me this notation indicates random variable correspondingly i is not i okay so
what averages a put in some kind of
events their later rate so if a is a what it means it means it means it is okay fine
opposite for the
confused or so a is ok it means that
at time a i played some
right so if this the whole expression with
these curly bases will be one if a time a i
played some common not i it will be zero if at time n i
played some common not i
okay so there is an additional couple of things you can observe about this so at any instant a is
equal to a will be one for some a okay for everything else
it will be
zero because  Every time instant I can
play only one common and at every time
instant I will play at least one common
so it will be one for one of several for everything else it will be
zero okay
so this
or this paper is not really the most
accessible
of the papers out there right so if you are
going to read it on your own you will have to do some
work okay so things are not I mean they are just as simple that
you are all really really
smart people reading the paper
so some of the gaps you have to fill in
yourself right I am just doing one of the
proofs in the paper so if you want to read the rest
of the paper and understand
the algorithm described in the paper so you
need to do some additional
work so let it be some arbitrary positive integer zero
so start of by
saying this
[music]
t running
variable
so number of times a played common I up until the
instant  There will be one and get from
the initial celebration plus k psv because all I could play
again the first k time first k
time I play ch am only once a and could was so
in first k psv there will be just one so I just have
the one and from
k psv trail till the eighth trial I do the
number of times this variable is one what did it mean
number of times I've taken am at so I will be I will
never take am so I just
sum up so number of
times I played am at what I get it
fine this expression fine okay this
is the only directly intuitive part that I have here so after this after this what ever you do
and this are all
standard tricks that people play to
bound random variables okay so to
actually tell you about the general
techniques for all of this I recommend you take the
ATTC
course because about third of the course it's all about how to do
proofs like this how many of you have done
TC
already advanced techniques in theoretical
computer science third of
computation okay it's a course that Jayalal
Sharma teaches in the CS department so it's very very
relevant to a lot of ML
research because a lot of machine learning has become like
randomize algorithms right so if the
people teach you how to analyze random
algorithms you can take the same ideas and
use them in analyzing machine learning
algorithms as well so a lot of the tools set
are developed there and useful here and many of the things we do here are essentially there
roots in the kind of analysis people do
for right anyway so we'll start off by
so we have arbitrary numbers okay a
set okay fine let's ask us that  I have played
the common l
times okay then let's start
counting
[praise] so as I keep going up till the next
step above l and greater than l only then will I
count the common pull so at some point I
discovered the common pull so okay as I added to my
count but not what I do I go ahead and look at
the correct count so far if the correct count is
higher and higher I'd have to make a count below a I don't want to count because I anyway am
starting to count from
a
okay so this is a slightly different way of doing it so I come and
start the count from some
arbitrary number given that I have taken that
arbitrary number already right so later on we all now we are going to bound this
expression some that at least l times I have
taken the
common right and then we will raise bound for a so that we get what ever
probability we want okay
so  That idea behind doing this so this I can now
write a bound for this amount I have done at
least l
times right then I will go back and find what is that
value of l so that I get what ever
probabilities I want right what ever
guarantee I want I will go and
find that a okay so Ashley what we are going to do is
okay I just need more
notation here to write this
but let me try this anyway so n am I
going to take am right now I will
take am I the
highest n a has the
highest value for this quantity
right now I will take am I one that has the highest
value for this quantity among all the
arms specifically I will take am only when
q ≥ c so that root term is now c right right
that root term then is what I have
written here a c so I will take am only when
q plus that c term is greater than
q of a star plus the c term
correspondingly
larger yes it's so I have a lesser than equal to here c
specifically this should be true right
in fact it has to be larger than everything else right
but at least it has to be larger than a
star correct so it is larger than every other
action but like he rightly pointed out so this
is a larger set than when I will
actually be taking the action but it's okay because I'm only trying to
upper bound it right I'm not trying
to give this exact
number because when I'm going to give this number it makes one right I'm just trying
to get this upper bound so I'm
saying very specifically I'm looking at
the best I'm saying that should be better than the
best to at least right so anything else
we need to have
l still need to have
this t condition is also there so we can put this
condition back
in
and t q u l l bucket mean q u l l
bucket rum r ibble
indicate have value of w expression win q u l l
bucket is true value of zero expression win q u l l bucket is false so this is counting how many
times this in quality became true after a been taken a
time so that is what we did yer right so this is
counting what ever we are doing yer i after l
times a has been taken because l i have
added here s count so likewise
I am counting the number of times this in
quality became true after a has been taken
l times so this is exactly what I have so far right were here either this seat or
another seat vacant or you want to move as well you can see everything your all
fine
rat no you don wa to  Complaint by I tell you why I do
n't know what I have written and I don't understand what is
written well subscribe it becomes small right large then it becomes
confusing
so see a few
people can read it I'm reading it out see
a human earn a star of a human basically the
number of times played a star till the a
few point
right note that I don't have to know this because I don't know what is
a star right this is just the but
you know that there is a star
right and I know that my I have to have a better what ever
quantity than a star
right so it's just that right I don't know I don't need to know which
is a star okay just don't
get confused by the fact that I am
using a star in the proof I get that c
a -1 earns t star m
-1 and this is
cm-1 t of
m-1 b  Previously not a star is the true
best action why you don't know anything about right because
for regret we have to
compare against the true best function right so
we are comparing against the true best
function right okay so far so good people can people could hear
me right and people understand was guy ra so
now i'm shifting over here
writing one line am talking for 10
minutes
man
[praise]
i really need to have an additional index
for the k function for us to say this that t now
so the k function at step a human ok
really need additional thing but keep changing o
time i need to note what stage talking
about k function so point am talking about
k function at a human
stage
right k function every stage can be the same as the
k function a stage if i had not taken the
action previously not a human stage if i'm not
taking action an more action i then at m
Stage also the queue function of action a will be the same it would have to
change it just you have to be careful about how
you interpret the
index and I hope I also don't mess it up does that so we do need a
different interpretation
for I do need additional notation above for that because we need to what we need
to insert
into this bound here the number of times I have
taken a star for so far
what we need to insert into this bound here the
number of times I have taken a star so far ch it a
star a may right
and so it becomes little cons this can be as this will be
a star and so okay fi you can get away with little
yard expression so what I'm saying here
is okay take the minimum of this
expression okay for all time instances zero to a
take the maximum of this
expression right for all time instances a
to a
and look  At number of times one will be
higher than the other right this will be an
over count of that
event it is clear right I am
talking about this
quantity being higher this
quantity at a particular instant at some time a minute
the
quantity for a star was less than the
quantity for a taking some time instant a
human at which this happens what I am talking about
okay at time a minute I look at all the
star value I had in the previous
time steps okay I will take the least of
that right and I will take all the values ​​of all the
values ​​I had in the previous time steps
I will take the maximum of that okay if the max
of this is greater than the minimum of that then I will
count that as one right so
can you convince yourself that that
event will certainly be
counted right because at that  Instant the
value is already greater so obviously the
max will be greater than the min right so if this is
not the
min rate min should be less than this so if this value is greater than this value by some quantity greater than this value is probably greater than some quantity less than this value so this is just
over count of the
event when writing this over
count because it makes it too early for me to write
this event rate exactly one
bucket for me to write
expression
or less
finish
or zero lesson a lesson a lesson because because I have the
condition right I have to have taken this at
least l times so the
first l time what happens I don't worry so I will
remove the rate never after that I am worried about
but this will be an over count  Okay, this will be an
overcount of that. It's a little bit
tricky here. So, in the
proof, actually, assums that at this
point, okay, I have taken this at least s
times, not t er a times. Okay, mainly because of this notation, it's a
translation problem, but we will see, we will
work with this, and then I will
probably adjust the results later.
Right, but if you are reading the proof, I am just telling you there is a
mismatch in the notation
that we are using. So, a
neat trick I have taken is to read all the min max and everything else, so what are we doing here? So,
assum t min arr
sum
index right, call
index p p
max arr sum index from p 2 and sum doing here. Summing
over all possible
instances for a star and summing over all
possible instances for
a correct, so the combination p1 p2 will be sum because
summing over l  Possible instance at some
point I would use p1 for a and p2 for
s. Correct because summing over l is a possible instance.
So what was p1? P1 was the one for
this minimum was achieved. P2 was the one for this
maximum was achieved. So summing over a at some
point s would have p0 at some point s would have
p2 at that point. This expression must be true because
I know from the min and max
arguments they must be true. So I will only be
counting this. I will be
over counting a. I will be counting
other things also but I will only be counting this. So far we have not lost anything but I am still maintaining it as an
upper bound. Okay, so we started off with this
event. Right now we have done a lot of
simplifications and kept losing the bound. This was a
Strict Equalities Nothing Here Ra This was a
strict quality no
approximations
It is counting a larger and larger event
Now the thing is I have come to a point where I have
a simple enough expression right I can can
try to bound directly no okay so you can
start thinking this kind of should
lead you to the use of tongue binding I can use
the use of tongue binding to try and bounce this
expression this simple enough expression okay okay so if this is
true this is true one can this happen
so my claim is this can be
true if none of several conditions hold
right so this can be true if s can be true if I am either
grossly underestimating
my
final action
value right so this is the final action equals now this is
the true
value Ra so the true value minus the
confidence
bound and others  Think about it. This is a
star plus the confidence bound. This lesson involves
grossly
underestimating
the true value. It's one thing, so that could be one
condition under which this could be true, what could be another condition?
You're grossly overestimating the true value. It's one thing, so that could be one condition under which this could be true, what could be another condition? You're grossly overestimating the true value. It's one thing, so that could be one condition under which this could be true, what could be another condition? You're grossly overestimating
the true value. It's one way I have to make a big mistake for my star, and I have to make a big mistake the other way for my star. I see the truth. I have to either come very far below
a true star
value. I mean a star, and I have to be much above my average. This is not going to happen. So, in the second condition, it's okay and can't happen with grossly overstating, underestimating, not to value. I'm close to value. I'm close to value. Other than that,
I really don't have to
grossly understate.  thing so it's
possible that I still could make an error in some other
condition
so I have my two values ​​my
take the confidence interval rate so I have
confidence it is my confidence interval
off right
side
so the confidence interval is taking the
confidence interval from my lower value
rate from the lower value I take the
confidence interval and upper value is the
optimal action value I have in the then I can
make a mistake with making mistakes
I am set to be close together
rate and close is a relative
term close is defined in terms of the current
uncertainty I have because this is
going to change every time I
take an action this is going to become smaller
and smaller rate so at the beginning of the
learning this can be quite large so I can still make a mistake even if I are
slightly far right so  The three
conditions are: one of this at least I have to be
satisfied for this one to become true second one to
second one so the first one says okay I have my I have
q of a
star and I have my confidence bound this is the
first one okay and the true q
star a star is then okay I grossly
underestimated q star this is one
condition so the second condition says this is
q of a is right and this is probably so
grossly overestimated q star
is equal to the second condition so this is
q is greater than q star plus the
confidence bound so this is the confidence bound
so q star plus this confidence bound will be only till here right
but q is greater
than this third result from the first second third third
result of the second no no yet another
condition that can
hold right  Neither of this don't hold also
I could still be making a mistake rat I could still this could still be one if
the true
means and not far apart
with respect to this error
bar basically what I am saying is
true why star could be somer her
rat but I still can make
mistake because it's too close probably draw
this picture and put it somer
permanently every time to be a ting
picture so first thing I have said was ok the
k star summer her rat I make
mistake t so then after this it is so it is
possible for me to make an
error ra and then other case was ok this k was somer
her possible to make mistake that third case none of this really need to happen rat true k
star could be well with in
the bauce rat but given the
current uncertainty I have in
my k off  aa right so the true means are not so far apart one can not true means aa exactly won
later I still make a mistake so the first
condition is true the second condition is true but
still made the mistake so
people have this expression everyone has it in their
notebooks people are writing
notes
people are not writing notes they have it in their
memory okay but I need to remember this okay so let's
look at
one so I wanted to look at the probability of a
star
or
so I wanted to buy
probability so can I told you a
capital kl m
s d r o n
b I told you the comparison rate I told
you the a capital k m e q star so you have
two right so as then r asn
became c a right and bound e e power mine a s a
right
and what is so to l n a ba a
squa plug it in  Simplify it and tell
me what the
answer is so what is it and what is it
plug in
expression yes this is it is the
bomb
lsi b paper
un rat b iut star star notation
itf so it becomes star of this thing s a
plug in r ar
ratan s
basically
so my
s get
cancel t a get l a come on all wd done
so far y could do
simplification l an just substitute this
into the and then cancel things out and tell
me what's
happening
by m power 4 right so essentially this will be less equal
to okay so what about the second
term
yes what about the third
term okay here is where we are going to
use our mysterious
l t what did a what did I
introduce l for I said that he I've done
so many number of trails already okay I'm
only looking at  The event after that many
number of times I have taken a
right so I am going to make the following
statement I've taken a right
six number of times
initially I have taken a right six number of times initially
This event never happened that is enough to satisfy this question so what do we have we have
q star a
star
minus star
i
minus 2 c
[music] I'm
okay so essentially I'm saying that it is at least this much that is enough so this means it is equal to this much it is at least this much if you remember that it is a
summation starts from
l right I consider it only from l so if I say
l is this so that means my t is at least this much
correct go and plug this into my c as
expression that is enough so if my t is this much at
least  This much
so what I get is I get by 8 ln
a delta s l go up so ln l l get
cancel so ba will become ba for
half half in delta
a rat so half and half to l get cancel all get
delta so this expression will
become rat and what is this equal to so for any value greater than this this
quantity l b greater zero times me in
quality l never hold kreak
people see
again yes okay so say a to be at least this much so
remember my t a a that si summation is
starting from a I am almost have
taken this already right
so I am almost have taken this l
times already so what I will do is I will
plug in this
value for the number of times a have
taken this already right this value so I will
plug in 8 l m right this is c m [ __ ] s
right so in this case look at this the
expression  is m and this so this will be 100
m
root so plugging in the root of a plug in 8
times 100 a divided by delta a
squared a will get canceled out
so 2 b will become 100 and divide by
delta a squared a will get canceled out so I basically get the
root of delta b for each delta a given number of times so I get
and plug in delta a squared a will get canceled out so I
return 100 m root so by definition of
delta a this expression is
zero and for values ​​larger if I
take the a a more times than this will become
greater than zero and then for that reason
the condition will never hold if I
take the a a at least if I take the a a
number of times r a is given by
the expression the third condition will never
hold okay so the probability of the third condition
holding is zero and a is greater  Then this right
so now what happens so the
probability
of this whole thing happening is bounded by just
two times this probability just does even so still not done are we so we are
bounding the expected
value of the thing right so we have
expected value
of
ask you to right this out are okay so this is lesson ill
8 l a ba delta s but e a plus
summation termed are a a
subset specific value for a are okay then what will be
the internal term here again we have this
random variable f could take
values ​​of one and zero so what is the
expected value of the random variable is just
the probability of it being one right so there are only
two of two things right so
the probability of this event plus the
probability of this event is basically
right so I am not writing down this because
This expression is going to take a long thing
so the probability of p probability of
that event so in which our case is just a
minus 4 to the power minus 4 to the power value 4 t
Ashley right so it's clear so you see how I came about right so here this was a
random
variable right now was taken the expectation
so you can replace the random variable with the
probability of it being one will be the
Expectation of the rum
variable
okay it's fine so so replace it with the
probability of it being one is upper bound a
minus 4 a minus 4 ats basically okay great
so this
summation is going to declare it to
converge to 1 ps s
bathan you can it's a little each thing but it's pure
algebra you can work it out
and standard relation you can look it up also r a so
basically what we have so this is you can kind
of see this is going to because it's
going to be a diminishing sum so it's
going to converge to a limit right and so
what is really interesting is this part right it's some
constant what ever it is that it
converges to it's not really of
interest you know not really of great
interest what is really of interest is
this 8 ln a ba delta a right because this
is the one where  You're going to get messed up
a lot because it has the long term right
and it also has your delta i square. But this
is just the expected value of
t. You multiply it
by delta i to get the total regret and
yaw to get the
overall yaw. So
essentially, the thing that we have finally is the
expression that I raise here. That is what you will end up with. You should keep that
in your mind because it is the final
expression you are going to end up with.
This is for each arm. This is for one
suboptimal arm. Right, this total number of
times you played it, we'll ride now. So the
regret due to the suboptimal arm will be
delta i times this number. So if the
delta i square goes to delta i in the
denominator of the original expression, I flip
back and look at the original expression. We have
delta i.  Yes, and we also had a
3 in Delta I, but this is for one, so you have to do this
for the suboptimal arms.
Basically, the calculation is overall I'm not
optimal, so this is done, we've got to avoid regret and we've seen it. The nice thing is, we've seen it,
the regret grows as we're getting,
and the result from the 80%
tails, as long as you can't have a regret
optimizing algorithm, it's better than none. What you can try
to improve it is that it's also impossible
to get rid of the
Delta I, it's also impossible to get rid of
you, because that means the arms are close
in reward, it becomes hard to eliminate the
bad
arms. If they are far away in reward, then you can
quickly figure out which arms are close
in reward.  It's become harder
to figure out so two things are important there
so two are essential components to it so
basically people find themselves with the to
okay and so it's essentially a law of work
that happens in regret optimality so I have to stop here because we have reached a full
clock I don't know how many of you
noticed it so if you haven't I will take that as I kept you
successfully
engaged but these people are just biding their
time to leave well I apologize for keeping here
for so long but I needed to finish this night I could have stopped halfway through
and
started in the next class with three sums or something so
the next class I
looked
at last optimality cr was talking about
cha was pack optimality
[music]
[applause]